Guide to the UE Legal Department Personnel Papers, 1940-1970s UE.9.1
ULS Archives & Special Collections
UE Legal Department Personnel Papers
1940-1970s
ULS Archives & Special Collections
United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America. Legal Department
UE.9.1
15 Linear Feet (12 boxes)
This subgroup contains the records of the United Electrical, Radio, and Machine Workers of America (UE) Legal Department staff. Records include correspondence and legal documents regarding War Labor Board cases and company information.
Scope and Content Notes
The Legal Department of the UE consisted of general and associate counsels that were responsible for representing the national union, as well as its locals and members, during legal hearings and cases. This subgroup contains the papers of Legal Department staff. Records include correspondence and legal documents regarding War Labor Board cases and company information. Documents regarding the draft status of UE staff are also present.
Arrangement
Series 9.1.1. Fred Livingston
Series 9.1.2. David Scribner
Series 9.1.3. Frank J. Donner
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of the United Electrical, Radio, and Machine Workers of America in 1976, 1986, and 1997.
Previous Citation
UE Legal Department Personnel Papers, 1940-1970s, UE.9.1, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Portions of this collection have been previously cited as Papers of Fred Livingston, Associate General Counsel, United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America (UE), 1940-45, UE:NO-ST-LivingstonF, Archives Service Center, University Library System, University of Pittsburgh
Related Material
UE Law Firm and Attorney Correspondence, 1943-1979, UE.9.6, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Federal Bureau of Investigation on the UE Records, 1940-1985, UE.9.5, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
UE Communism Collection, 1935-1968, UE.10.2.1, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Hymen Schlesinger Papers, 1927-1990, AIS.1977.33, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Personnel records; Legal documents; Correspondence; Labor lawyers -- United States; Group insurance -- United States; Labor; Draft -- United States -- History -- World War, 1939-1945; Draft registration -- United States – History -- World War, 1939-1945; Labor unions -- Organizing -- United States; Labor unions -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Electric industry workers -- Labor unions -- United States -- History; United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America -- History; Donner, Frank J.; Livingston, Frederick R.; Scribner, David; United States. National War Labor Board (1942-1945); United States. Selective Service System
- Fred Livingston, 1936-1945; 9.1.1.
  Scope and Contents note
  Frederick R. Livingston was born in November 1912. In 1944 Livingston left the federal National Labor Relations Board (NLRB) to become the Associate General Counsel of the UE. In this capacity, Livingston advised the union and represented it before the draft board, War Labor Board, and War Manpower Commission during World War II.
  The first two boxes in this series contain materials regarding the draft status of UE staff. The memorandum produced by the UE for the Director of Selective Service is particularly interesting since it provides justification for deferring international officers from military service and stresses the UE's importance to the war effort. The draft questionnaires, arranged alphabetically by last name of staff member, provide biographical information often not available elsewhere and shed light on staff members' roles in the union and war economy. Correspondence with Selective Service and the local draft boards is also included.
  The rest of this series includes research on group insurance for the union. Several of these files relate directly to the creation of the 1944 pamphlet "UE Guide to Group Insurance" designed to assist UE locals negotiating insurance policies with their companies. Included is correspondence with attorneys, UE districts, UE locals, and other CIO unions concerning insurance policies. Also present is a set of questionnaires from a survey conducted by the UE national office to determine the amount of insurance coverage obtained at the local union level. Several information files exist for individual insurance companies and policies. Additional files bring together War Labor Board cases from 1943 to 1945 focused on determining whether unions were to be permitted to acquire group insurance benefits or not.
  - Affidavit – Occupational Classification, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - CIO Review Committee on Draft Committee, 1942-1944 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Classification Advice, 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence – Selective Service, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Deferred Indefinitely, 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Draft Deferment, 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 06-07)
  - Draft Miscellaneous, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Memorandum on the Draft Status of Staff – Deferments, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 09-14)
  - Names of Companies Recommending Occupational Deferment, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Newspaper Items, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Occupational Deferment by District, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 17-25)
  - General Information on Questionnaire on Draft, 1942-1944 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Questionnaire on Draft, A-B, 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 27-34)
  - Questionnaire on Draft, C, 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 35-39)
  - Questionnaire on Draft, D, 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 40-48)
  - Questionnaire on Draft, E, 1942-1945 (Box 2, Folder 01-02)
  - Questionnaire on Draft, F, 1942-1945 (Box 2, Folder 03-08)
  - Questionnaire on Draft, G, 1942-1945 (Box 2, Folder 09-11)
  - Questionnaire on Draft, H, 1942-1945 (Box 2, Folder 12-15)
  - Questionnaire on Draft, I, 1942-1945 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Questionnaire on Draft, J, 1942-1945 (Box 2, Folder 17-19)
  - Questionnaire on Draft, K, 1942-1945 (Box 2, Folder 20-22)
  - Questionnaire on Draft, L, 1942-1945 (Box 2, Folder 23-26)
  - Questionnaire on Draft, M, 1942-1945 (Box 2, Folder 27-36)
  - Questionnaire on Draft, N, 1942-1945 (Box 2, Folder 37-40)
  - Questionnaire on Draft, O, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Questionnaire on Draft, P, 1942-1944 (Box 2, Folder 42-43)
  - Questionnaire on Draft, R, 1942-1945 (Box 2, Folder 44-49)
  - Questionnaire on Draft, S, 1942-1945 (Box 2, Folder 50-55)
  - Questionnaire on Draft, T, 1941-1945 (Box 2, Folder 56-58)
  - Questionnaire on Draft, V-W, 1942-1945 (Box 2, Folder 59-61)
  - Questionnaire on Draft, Z, 1943-1944 (Box 2, Folder 62-63)
  - Requested Draft Deferments, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - War Department, 1942-1944 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Analysis of UE Local Plans, 1944-1945 (Box 3, Folder 01-02)
  - Car Accident Case, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Companies: Aetna Life Insurance Company, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Companies: Associated Hospital Service, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Companies: Connecticut General Life Insurance, 1943-1944 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Companies: Equitable Insurance Company, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Companies: Group Health Co-Operative, 1943-1944 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Companies: John Hancock Life Insurance, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Companies: Metropolitan Life Insurance Company, 1936-1942 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Companies: Miscellaneous, 1944-1945 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Companies: Prudential Life Insurance, 1944-1945 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Companies: Savings Bank Life Insurance, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Companies: Trade Union Accident and Health, 1943-1944 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Companies: Trade Union Agency Insurance, 1942-1944 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence: Attorneys, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence: CIO Unions, 1943-1944 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence: Miscellaneous, 1944-1945 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence: State Capitols and Washington, 1943-1944 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence: UE Districts and Locals, 1943-1945 (Box 3, Folder 20-21)
  - Fitzgerald, Albert – Accident Policy, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Miscellaneous, 1943-1944 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Newspaper Articles, 1944-1945 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Pension Plans, 1944-1945 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Insurance Plans: Associated with the UE, 1944-1945 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Insurance Plans: District 4, 1942-1944 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Insurance Plans: General Electric, 1940-1945 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Insurance Plans: Miscellaneous, 1943-1944 (Box 3, Folder 29-30)
  - Insurance Plans: New York City, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Insurance Plans: Under Current Contract, 1943-1944 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Policy at UE National Office, 1944-1945 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Policy Proposals to UE, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Questionnaire to Locals on Insurance Coverage, 1944-1945 (Box 4, Folder 03-05)
  - Requests for Books and Information, 1943-1945 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Simons and Greeley – Employee Benefit Plans, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Specimen Insurance Policies, 1943-1944 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Taxation, 1944 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - UE Guide to Group Insurance: Letters and Clippings, 1944-1945 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - UE Guide to Group Insurance: Plates, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Veterans, 1944 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Wagner-Murray-Dingell Bill on Social Security, 1944-1945 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - War Labor Board Case: Dissenting Opinion, 1944 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - War Labor Board Case: Representatives' Correspondence, 1943-1944 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - War Labor Board Case: Rulings on Group Insurance, 1943-1945 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Worksheets, 1943-1945 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Workers Compensation, 1944 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Group Insurance: Correspondence and UE Staff Files, undated (Box 05-07)
- David Scribner, 1943-1945; 9.1.2.
  David Scribner served as General Counsel for the UE during the 1940s to the 1950s. He represented the union throughout the hearings of the House Un-American Activities Committee (HUAC) and other ensuing trials accusing members of the UE to be members of the Communist Party. His work with the UE and other cases in which he believed a defendant's civil rights were being compromised led to him being investigated by the FBI. Scribner was also a founder of the National Lawyers Guild and served as executive secretary in 1959. He died in April 1991.
  This series contains many files regarding National and regional War Labor Board cases concerning UE locals and their companies. Included are correspondence, clippings, and legal documents. Publications on companies and certified public accountants in New York are also present.
  - Local 456 Negotiations and War Labor Board Case, 1943 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Smith-Connaly Strike Vote, GE-GM, Westinghouse, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - General Electric and Westinghouse, War Labor Board, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - War Labor Board Transcript, Breeze Corp., 1944 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Westinghouse and GE, War Labor Board Cases, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Westinghouse War Labor Board Joint Application, 1943-1945 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - GE War Labor Board Joint Applications, 1944 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - War Labor Board Cases and Correspondence, undated (Box 09-10)
- Frank J. Donner, 1950-1967; 9.1.3.
  Frank Donner earned his law degree from Columbia University and soon after became a staff attorney for the NLRB. He then served as counsel for the Congress of Industrial Organizations from 1943 to 1947, when he started his own firm. He specialized in defending people questioned by HUAC and was himself accused of being a Communist during the hearings. These experiences led to him becoming general counsel for the UE during the 1960s. He wrote several books, including The Un-Americans, and from 1971 until his death in 1993, he was director of the American Civil Liberties Union Project on Political Surveillance at Yale Law School.
  This series contains office files of Frank Donner. Included are correspondence, address books, business cards, and records from his law firm. Some personal correspondence is also present.
  - Donner, Perlin & Piel, Settlement of Firm Accounts, undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Danny Donner-School, 1959-1966 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence regarding Ballantine Book, 1961-1963 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Lillian Hellman, 1950-1960 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Ballantine Books Correspondence, 1962-1965 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Albany-Georgia Suit-Temporary, 1959 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Talks-Articles-Book, Carey McWilliams, 1960-1965 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence with Arthur Kinoy-Research Project, 1963 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Clippings on McCarthy and the UE, 1954 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Frank J. Donner Misc., undated (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Memos and Correspondence, 1958-1962 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Arbitration, 1976 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1976 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Student Draft, 1968-1969 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, January 1966-December 1967 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Jacobson, 1970-1971 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence on the Right Wing, 1962-1963 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - L.M. Rabinowitz Foundation, 1962 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Personal Correspondence, A-L, 1960-1961 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Personal Correspondence, A-L, 1959-1962 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Guns-Gun Control, 1968 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Donner & Piel-Financial, 1964 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Personal Correspondence, M-Z, 1959-1962 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Personal Correspondence, A-L on the Right Wing, 1963 (Box 12, Folder 13)